A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, Compiled by Elizabeth Langhorne 1839-1990
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Rives Family Papers, Compiled by Elizabeth Langhorne 1839-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10596-d
150 items
This collection contains Rives family correspondence, photographs, biographical and genealogical sketches, 1839-1990, along with research notes and letters compiled by Elizabeth Langhorne.
Elizabeth Langhorne
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Elizabeth Coles Langhorne.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of papers of the Rives family, of Albemarle County, Va., 1839-1990, compiled by Elizabeth Langhorne. The papers contain family correspondence, together with photographs, biographical and genealogical sketches, and research notes and letters compiled by Langhorne.
Family correspondence discusses a feud between family members, a Johns Hopkins position for William Cabell Rives, Jr., efforts to finance a school in Rochester, N.Y., estate settlement, Amelie Rives's "The Quick or the Dead?", family news including deaths, marriages and a divorce, and genealogical information. Of interest is a copy of a letter to Judith Page Walker Rives from Robert E. Lee extending condolences on the death of her husband William Cabell Rives.
The collection also contains two poems by Judith Page Walker Rives.
Contents List
- Rives Family Letters
  - Letters to Bishop Philip Mercer, Helen (Hamilton) Rhinelander, and Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy
    - Discussing the death of cousin William Cabell Rives 1939 Jan 2
    - Writing her appreciation for the financial assistance to her family, and the difficulties of her sister Gertrude (Rives) Potts 1940 Oct 10
    - Landon Rives, expressing her deep gratitude for the financial assistance for Gertrude (Rives) Potts 1940 Oct 1
    - News of Gertrude's health 1940 Nov 2
    - Friendly, Personal 1940 Nov 7
    - Giving details of her actions concerning the check sent for Gertrude (Rives) Potts 1940 Dec 19
    - Re Gertrude's husband Allen Potts and son Thomas R. Potts telling "tales of our iniquities," claim that Pierre and Amelie drove her from "Castle Hill"; ongoing feud between "Happy Creek" and Castle Hill"; mentions a friend, Leslie Hepburn Beckler, who was a professor of Law of the University of Virginia, 1929-1956 1940 Dec 29
    - Thomas R. Potts to Mrs. Rhinelander, writing on behalf of his mother, Gertrude (Rives) Potts, extending belated condolences on the death of Bishop Rhinelander and thanking her for the financial support 1941 Jan 10
    - Re Thomas R. Pott's recent cooperation 1941 Jan 14
    - Mrs. Rhinelander to Princess Troubetzkoy, re the situation with Gertrude (Rives) Potts 1941 Jan 17
    - Re family difficulties, Gertrude (Rives) Potts 1941 Jan 24
    - Re a visit from Louise Potts concerning the gravity of Gertrude's illness 1941 Feb 5
  - Letters to William Cabell Rives, Jr. 1876-1888
    - Francis Robert Rives (1822-1891) offering contribution toward the church cemetery in Albemarle County, Virginia 1876 Jan 1
    - Robert C. Winthrop re communication with D.C. Gilman, enclosing letter from DCG, concerning the placement of WCR, Jr. as a teacher at Johns Hopkins University 1876 Jan 24
    - William Cabell Rives, Jr. re WCR III's illness 1878 Oct 8
    - Robert C. Winthrop re Johns Hopkins University trustees meeting around February to discuss candidates 1880 Sep 8
    - Ella Rives (1834-1892) seeking help in purchasing a new carpet for their mother's bedroom, re farm operations and local news 1881 Apr 14
    - Thomas Underwood Dudley (1837-1904), Bishop, re officiating in All Saints Chapel, Newport, Rhode Island 1884 July 11
    - Anna Pell re Dr. Mercer's estate, enclosing letter from Samuel Robertson Honey (1842-1927), attorney, discussing conditions of a charitable organization receiving a portion of Dr. Mercer's estate 1884 July 14
    - Thomas Underwood Dudley accepting the Rives' invitation 1884 July 19
    - J.E. Macfarland re difficulties in beginning a school for boys in Rochester, now a teacher of French in the Rochester Female Academy and another institution conducted by Miss Doolittle, seeking a small loan for the purpose of forming a joint association with Miss Doolittle in the conduct and management of her school 1884 July 22
    - Martin Brimmer re Macfarland and his schemes and his struggle against ill fortune 1884 July 25
    - J.E. Macfarland in appreciation of his assistance 1884 July 28
    - Martin Brimmer re Macfarland, his admiration of J.W. Rogers 1884 July 3
    - Ella Rives discussing bad manners of the young people, fixing up a little cottage at "Beauval" 1886 June 29
    - Francis Robert Rives referring to The Quick and the Dead1888 May 12
  - Letters to William Cabell Rives III 1896-1933
    - Grace Winthrop Sears Rives (1828- ) discourse on the wedding of Gertrude Rives and Allen Potts 1896 Oct 21
    - Alexander Brown (1843-1906) re death of his sister, Lucy Rives Boles in London, England, his own reply to Mr. Henry in The Virginia Historical Magazine1899 Jan 24
    - W.W. Scott, State Library, Richmond, Virginia referring to the friendship of his father-in-law John Willis and William Cabell Rives' grandfather, William Cabell Rives, and inquiring as to the location of Willis' Buck's History of Virginia lent to his grandfather 1899 Mar 7
    - Gertrude Rives Potts re problems with Amelie and John Armstrong Chanler ruining her character 1909 Oct 12
    - Ethel King to Mrs. William Cabell Rives 1927 Nov 19
    - Annie Rives C. Owen re genealogical information of Rives, Saunders, and Pollard families 1931 May 26
    - Margaret Walker Morgan re genealogical information on the Walker family of "Castle Hill," with chart of Dr. Thomas Walker's descendants 1932 May 26
    - Gertrude Rives Potts, family news, divorce of Thomas R. Potts and his wife, Katherine 1930 July 25
    - Gertrude Rives Potts, final divorce of TRP, now legal guardian of their children, mentions Amelie and Landon Rives 1932 Nov 26
    - Gertrude Rives Potts, re his kindness, a falling out with "Castle Hill" family, her own family problems, her son Tom running away and marrying a sixteen year old girl, then divorcing, and marrying a very undesirable woman, and her poor health 1933 Dec 22
- Bill for five rings 1841 July 1
- Poems, "The Bridal Wreath" and "A Maiden to Marry! Dowry $100,000!!!" written by Judith Page Walker Rives 1871
- Research Papers of Elizabeth Coles Langhorne
  - "Castle Hill," Albemarle County
  - Amelie Rives [Troubetzkoy] 1974-1990, n.d.
  - Amelie Louise Rives [Sigourney] 1967
  - Judith Page Walker Rives 1861, 1882, 1964
  - William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) 1966, 1972, n.d.
  - William Cabell Rives: Breeder of Thoroughbreds and Hunters 1857, 1937, n.d.
  - Rives Family: Fine Arts
  - Rives Family: Photographs 1975-1990, n.d.
  - Biographical and Genealogical Sketches, and Miscellaneous 1915, 1978, n.d.
  - Letters to Elizabeth Coles Langhorne 1983-1984